Most traders lose money.
Not some.
Most.
Studies show around 70 to 80 percent of retail traders end up in the red.
But here's the thing nobody talks about — losing money isn't the bottom of the
ladder.
There are actually levels below that.
And the scary part?
Most people never even realize which level they're on.
we're mapping out every level of trading skill — from the person who just
downloaded Robinhood because their coworker mentioned GameStop,
all the way to the rare operators running systematic strategies that generate
returns regardless of what the market does.
Each level has its own blind spots.
Its own psychology.
Its own relationship with risk and money.
And most importantly,
its own version of the same core mistake — just dressed up differently.
The goal isn't to make you feel good or bad about where you are.
The goal is to show you exactly where you stand, what the next level looks like,
and what it actually takes to get there.
Because the path from Level 1 to Level 5 isn't about finding a better strategy.
It's about a complete rewiring of how you think.
Let's get into it.
1 is where almost everyone starts.
You've got a brokerage account, a Reddit thread,
maybe a TikTok algorithm feeding you stock tips between cat videos.
You buy something because it went up recently.
You sell it because it went down and scared you.
That's it.
That's the entire strategy.
There's no thesis.
No framework.
Just vibes and hope dressed up as conviction.
The Level 1 trader thinks they're investing.
They're not.
They're gambling with extra steps.
And the dangerous part isn't even losing money — it's when you make money early.
A beginner's luck win at Level 1 is one of the most financially
destructive things that can happen to a person.
Because now you have evidence that you're good at this.
You're not.
You got lucky in a rising market.
Every Level 1 trader eventually learns this lesson.
The only variable is how expensive the tuition is.
The tell-tale sign you're here?
You check your portfolio more than twice a day and you feel
physically anxious when it's red.